Preliminary Guide to the Clement C. Clay Papers, 1846-1972 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Clement C. Clay papers 1846-1970 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Clay, Clement C., 1905-1978.
3.50 linear feet Extent: 2,803 Items
Physician; member of the Clay family of Alabama; headed a photographic unit in the Medical Corps of the U.S. Navy in WWII; also served in the Hospital Division of the Medical Corps in that war. Later served as a hospital administrator and taught at a number of universities including the American University in Beirut, University of Chicago, Columbia University and Yale University. His consulting service included work for N.C. Memorial Hospital. Collection includes Clay family correspondence, Clement Clay's professional and military correspondence, and writings, including a number of presentations and reports. There are also scrapbooks, and two photographs of C.C. Clay, II as a child.
RL.00246
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Clement C. Clay Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1978.
Biographical Note
Clement Claiborne Clay, hospital administrator and professor, was born in Birmingham, Alabama, on Dec. 8, 1905 and was raised in Atlanta and Minneapolis. He received his A.B. from Columbia University in 1927 and his medical degree from McGill University in 1932. After an internship at St. John’s Riverside Hospital in Yonkers, NY, he attended the University of Chicago School of Business as a Julius Rosenwald Fellow in Hospital Administration.
After military service in the U.S. Navy during World War II, Clay became the founder and first director of the Program in Hospital Administration at the Yale University School of Medicine. In 1954 he was named Associate Professor of Administrative Medicine at the Columbia University School of Public Health and Co-Director of the Graduate Program in Hospital Administration. He became sole Director of the program in 1961 and was made a full professor in 1965.
Clay retired in January 1970; he died January 16, 1978.
[Biographical information taken from finding aid to the Clement C. Clay Papers at Columbia University Health Sciences Library Archives and Special Collections.]
Collection Overview
Collection includes Clay family correspondence, Clement Clay's professional and military correspondence, and writings, including a number of presentations and reports. There are also scrapbooks, and two photographs of C.C. Clay as a child.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Clay family; Clay, Clement C., 1905-1978; United States. Dept. of the Navy. Medical Service Corps; United States. Navy -- Medical care -- History; Medicine, Naval -- United States -- History; Physicians’ writings, American; Hospital administrators -- United States; Photographs; Scrapbooks
Related Material
Clement C. Clay Papers, 1917-1977 (bulk 1925-1970)
Columbia University Health Sciences Library Archives and Special Collections
C. C. Clay Papers, 1811-1925
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1846-1970 and undated, (14 boxes)
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1846-1926, unaccessioned papers (Box 1)
  - 1927-1930 (Box 2)
  - 1931-1935 (Box 3)
  - 1936-1940 (Box 4)
  - 1941-1945 (military) (Box 5)
  - 1941-1943 June (Box 6)
  - 1943 July-1945 Mar. (Box 7)
  - 1945 Apr.-1945 Dec. (Box 8)
  - 1946-1949 (Box 9)
  - 1950-1951 (Box 10)
  - 1954 July-1956 Dec. (Box 11)
  - 1952 Jan.-1954 June (Box 12)
  - 1957-1970 (Box 13)
  - 1931-1969 (professional) (Box 14)
- Writings Series, (2 boxes)
  - Writings (Box 15-16)
- Miscellaneous Papers Series, (1 box)
  - Clippings (Box 17)
  - Printed material
  - Financial papers
  - Legal papers
  - Pictures (photographs)
  - Volumes
- Addition (1987 Mar. 23), 1898-1970, (1 box)
  - Clippings (Box 18)
  - Correspondence
  - Printed material
  - Addresses and writings
  - Photograph of John Withers Clay
  - Biography and genealogy
  - Scrapbook
- Oversize Material
  - Clay family genealogy, 1443-1943 (Opaperfolder 1)
  - Scrapbook, circa 1853-1861 (Box OV1)